Finding Aid for the Medical Artifacts Collection
Eskind Biomedical Library Manuscripts Collection
- Shelf 10 1031 Laennec, René Théophile-Hyacinthe. Framed photographic reproduction of a picture of Rene Théophile-Hyacinthe Laennec (1781-1826) and the title page of his book entitled: Traite de l’Ausculation Médiate: et des Maladies des Poumon et du Coeur (Second Edition, Paris, 1826). Added to inventory June 8, 1995.
- Shelf 10 1032 Malpighi, Marcello. Framed photographic reproduction of a picture of Marcello Malpighi (1628-1694) and the title page of his book entitled: De Pulmonibus Observatione Anatomicae.. (Frankfort, 1683). Added to inventory June 8, 1995.
- Shelf 11 1033 Laennec, René Théophile-Hyacinth. Framed color print illustration of Rene Theophile Hyacinth Laennec (1781-1826). Copyright The Heart Bulletin, 1952. Added to inventory June 8, 1995.
- Shelf 11 1034 Einthoven, Wilhelm. Framed color print illustration of Wilhelm Einthoven (1860-1927). Copyright The Heart Bulletin, 1952. Added to inventory June 8, 1995.
- Shelf 11 1035 Auenbrugger, Joseph Leopold. Framed color print illustration of Joseph Leopold Auenbrugger (1722-1809). Copyright The Heart Bulletin, 1952. Added to inventory June 8, 1995.
- Shelf 11 1036 Withering, William. Framed color print illustration of William Withering (1741-1799). Copyright The Heart Bulletin, 1952. Added to inventory June 8, 1995.
- Shelf 13 1037 Foshee, John Clinton. Framed, hand-lettered certificate presented to John Clinton Foshee, M.D. by the Medical staff of Butterworth Hospital, Grand Rapids Michigan, for outstanding work, June 23, 1959. Added to inventory June 9, 1995.
- Shelf 13 1038 Vanderbilt University School of Medicine. Division of Radiology. Framed hand-drawn announcement of The Robert K. Rhamy and Harry S. Shelley Lectureship in Urology presented by Richard Turner-Warwick May 27, 1972. Added to inventory June 9, 1995. Donated by Dr. Harry S. Shelley.
- Shelf 13 1039 Shelley, Harry S. Framed certificate form the Vanderbilt Urology Society certifying that Dr. Harry S. Shelley is a senior member of the society, October 28, 1975. Added to inventory June 9, 1995. Donated by Dr. Harry S. Shelley.
- Shelf 13 1040 Vanderbilt University School of Medicine. Phi Chi. Wooden plaque for the Eben J. Carey Memorial Award in Anatomy presented annually in each Phi Chi Chapter to the student having the highest average in anatomy during his freshman year. Recipients with plates include: J. B. Otis 1958-59, J. C. Overall 1959-60, A.R. Lawton III 1960-61, J. B. Black 1961-62, and S. P. Hawes III 1963-64. Added to inventory June 9, 1995.
- Shelf 13 1041 American Nurses Association. Framed needlepoint representation of the circular blue beige and black seal of the A. N. A. “IM 77" stitched at bottom. Added to inventory June 9, 1995.
- Shelf 14 1042 International Congress of Medical Librarianship. Framed group photo of the First International Congress of Medical Librarianship, London, 1953. Added to inventory June 9, 1995.
- Shelf 14 1043 International Congress of Medical Librarianship. Framed group photo of the Second International Congress of Medical Librarianship, Washington, D.C. June 16-22, 1963. Added to inventory June 9, 1995.
- Shelf 22 1044 Flexner, Simon. Framed and autographed photograph of Dr. Simon Flexner in laboratory setting, ca.1925. Donated by Vanderbilt Department of Pathology, Dr. John M. Flexner, and Dr. Robert Collins May 3, 1995.
- Shelf 22 1045 Welch, William H. Framed photograph of Dr. William Welch in his office at Johns Hopkins. Ca. 1920. Donated by Vanderbilt Department of Pathology, Dr. John M. Flexner, and Dr. Robert Collins May 3, 1995.
- Shelf 22 1046 Vanderbilt University School of Medicine. Framed group photograph of the professors and associate professors of the newly reorganized Vanderbilt University School of Medicine. Taken in 1925 at the North Portico entrance of the old hospital building. Labeled on back. Donated by Vandebrilt Department of Pathology, Dr. John M. Flexner, and Dr. Robert Collins May 3, 1995.
- Shelf 22 1047 Goodpasture, Ernest William. Group photograph of the pathology house staff at Johns Hopkins in 1912 (including Dr. Ernest Goodpasture) assembled around Drs. William Welch and George Whipple. Labeled on back. Donated by Vanderbilt Department of Pathology, Dr. John M. Flexner, and Dr. Robert Collins May 3, 1995.
- Shelf 22 1048 Vanderbilt University Medical Center. Framed aerial view of Vanderbilt Medical Center, ca 1985. Donated by Robert Vantrease, June 1995.
- Shelf 22 1049 Vanderbilt University School of Medicine. Diabetes-Endocrinology Center. Framed collage of photographs relating to the establishment of the Vanderbilt University Diabetes-Endocrinology Center, September 1973. Persons include: Mayor Richard Fulton, Dr. Oscar Crofford, Alexander Heard and Dr. Philip Felts. Donated by Dr. Oscar Crofford June 16, 1995.
- Shelf 22 1050 Vanderbilt University School of Medicine. Class of 1995. Poster board with two color prints of the front and rear view of an alabaster sculpture created by Somers Randolph and donated by the Class of 1995 to the Eskind Biomedical Library in 1995. Donated by Vanderbilt Medical School Class of 1995. Deposited by Robert Vantrease, June 27, 1995.
- MCN 1st 1051 Witherspoon, John Alexander. Gold-framed oil on canvass portrait of Dr. John Alexander Witherspoon, Professor of Clinical Medicine at Vanderbilt from 1896 to 1929. Artist unknown. Canvass covered by glass. Good condition, restored in 1995. Added to inventory June 29, 1995.
- MCN 1st 1052 Eve, Duncan Sr. Gold-framed oil on canvass portrait of Dr. Duncan Eve, Sr., Professor of Clinical Surgery at Vanderbilt from 1896-1937. Painted by. Good condition, restored in 1995. Canvass covered by glass Added to inventory June 29, 1995.
- MCN 5th Bunny Burson removed to hang in Light Hall. January 24, 1997 1053 Bryan, Worcester Allen. Gold-framed oil on canvass portrait of Dr. Worcester Allen Bryan, Professor of Clinical Surgery at Vanderbilt from 1911 to 1940. Painted by Henry L. Wolff in 1941. Good condition, canvass covered by glass. Added to inventory June 29, 1995.
- MCN 5th 1054 Johnson, Samuel Earl. Gold-framed oil on canvass portrait of Commander Samuel Earl Johnson, M.D. He was a 1911 Vanderbilt University School of Medicine graduate who was killed in action December 7, 1941 aboard the U.S.S. Arizona at Pearl Harbor. Painted by Louise Cone in 1940. Added to inventory June 29, 1995.
- MCN 5th 1055 Garrey, Walter E. Gold-framed oil on canvass portrait of Dr. Walter E. Garrey, Professor of Physiology from 1925 to 1944. Name of artist in lower right hand corner is indecipherable. Added to inventory June 29, 1995.
- MCN 5th 1056 Framed oil on canvass portrait of an unidentifed person by Hugh Walter in 1953. Damaged, paint is flaking off canvass. Added to inventory July 10, 1995.
- Shelf 16 1057 Wilkes, Susan. Framed water color of the feet of a patient suffering from arteriosclerosis gangrene. Painted by Susan Wilkes in 1928. Added to inventory July 11, 1995
- Shelf 9 1058 Hardy, Sir William B. Framed photograph of Sir William B. Hardy, Director of Low Temperature Research, Cambridge University, and Flexner Lecturer in 1931. Autographed. Added to inventory July 10, 1995. Donated by Amos Christie.
- Map Case Drawer 1 1059 Gwathmey, James Tayloe. Framed photograph of James Tayloe Gwathmey (1862-1944). Added to inventory August 3, 1995.
- Shelf 2 1060A-B Mercurial air holder and breathing machine. Framed print illustration of mercurial air holder and breathing machine. Added to inventory August 3, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 1 1061 Pettenkofer, Max von. Mounted and laminated print of a portrait of Max von Pettenkofer (1818-1901). Added to inventory, August 3, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 1 1062 Liebig, Justus von. Mounted and laminated print of a portrait of Justus von Liebig (1803-1873). Added to inventory, August 3, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 1 1063 ICNND Nutrition Survey- Ethiopia. Photograph, mounted on cardboard relating to the 1958 ICNND Nutrition Survey in Ethiopia. Picture is of a man plowing a field with a team of oxen. Added to inventory, August 3, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 1 1064 ICNND Nutrition Survey- Ethiopia. Photograph, mounted on cardboard relating to the 1958 ICNND Nutrition Survey in Ethiopia. Picture is of a doctor administering an oral examination to a patient. Added to inventory, August 3, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 1 1065 ICNND Nutrition Survey- Ethiopia. Photograph, mounted on cardboard relating to the 1958 ICNND Nutrition Survey in Ethiopia. Picture is of a doctor testing a woman’s arm for body fat. Added to inventory, August 3, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 1 1066 Southern Medical Association. Composite photograph of Presidents of the Southern Medical Association, 1906-1937. Added to inventory, August 3, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 1 1067 Medical Library Association. Wide-angle lens photograph of the Convention Banquet of the Medical Library Association meeting, Hotel Kenmore, Boston, Massachusetts, June 20-23, 1950. Added to inventory, August 3, 1995.
- Shelf 22 1068 Welch, William H. Framed and photograph of a portrait of William H. Welch. Inscribed by Dr. Welch to the artist of the portrait, Thomas S. Corner. Presented to Dr. Waller S. Leathers by Thomas S. Corner, in April 1938, and in turn presented to the library by Dr. Leathers. Added to inventory, August 4, 1995. Donated by Dr. Waller S. Leathers
- Shelf 5 1069 Hillman, J. William Framed photograph of Dr. J. William Hillman. Appointed Assistant Professor of Orthopedic Surgery in 1952, he became Professor and Chairman of the Department in 1959 and held the post until his death in 1971. Portrait by Fabian Bacharach. Transferred by Vanderbilt Department of Orthopedics, August 4, 1995.
- Shelf 1 1070 Fischer, Johann W. Framed hand-drawn diagram of various human bones by Johann W. Fischer (1740-1820). Captions hand-written in German. Drawn March 17, 1770. Inscribed by Dr. Bernard Weinstien: “To one of the best guys about the joint.” Transferred by Vanderbilt Department of Orthopedics, August 9, 1995.
- Shelf 22 1071 Carpenter George K. Framed print of a hand-drawn certificate of appreciation given to Dr. George K. Carpenter on the occasion of his 70th birthday by the Trial Lawyers and Judges of Nashville, February 15, 1967. Contains over 150 signatures. Transferred by Vanderbilt Department of Orthopedics, August 9, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 1 1072 Youmans, John B. Black and white photograph of a portrait of Dr. John B. Youmans by Martin Kellogg matted on yellow cardboard. Added to inventory August 9, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 1 1073 Pilcher, Cobb. Color photograph of the portrait of Cobb Pilcher by Martin Kellogg. Added to inventory, August 9, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 2 1074 Vantrease, Robert. Drawings for current periodical shelving and plexiglass book support by Robert Vantrease, February 1966. Added to inventory, August 9, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 2 1075 Nashville Medical History. Map of Nashville showing location of medical schools. Drawn by Robert Vantrease used in Rudolph H. Kampmeier’s Vanderbilt University School of Medicine: The Story in Pictures.. illustration number 29. Added to inventory, August 9, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 2 1076 Vanderbilt Medical Library. Original lettering and graphs made for slides for a presentation to the Executive Faculty, by Eleanor G. Steinke, Director of Vanderbilt Medical Library, July 8, 1965. Added to inventory, August 9, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 2 1077 Vanderbilt Medical Library. Poster board with graph scale showing expansion of Vanderbilt Medical Library 1925-1935. Added to inventory, August 9, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 2 1078 Vanderbilt Medical Center Library. Poster board containing a hand-drawn and lettered map which shows the collection size by volume of school, hospital and medical society libraries in Middle and East Tennessee. Ca. 1975. Added to inventory, August 9, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 2 1079 Vanderbilt University School of Medicine Department of Pathology. Poster board containing a composite of gross and pathologic photographs of Granuloma Inguinale -- lesions and Donovan organisms. Ca. 1935. Added to inventory August 10, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 2 1080 Vanderbilt University School of Medicine, Department of Pathology. Poster board containing a composite of gross and pathologic photographs and illustrations of Molluscum contagiosum (some being plates from journals, and one being an original hand-drawn and colored illustration by Elizabeth B. Hibbs in 1932). Added to inventory, August 10, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 2 1081 Vanderbilt University School of Medicine, Department of Pathology. Poster board containing a composite of gross and pathologic photographs and illustrations of Trachoma inclusion. Blennorrhea, and Psittacosis. (some being plates from journals, and others being original hand-drawn and colored-- one by Elizabeth B. Hibbs in 1932).
- Map Case Drawer 2 1082A-C Wilkes, Susan B. Original illustrations made by Susan B. Wilkes made for the book Essentials of the Diagnostic Examination, 1940 by John B. Youmans. Three poster boards two of which contain ten drawings including drawing blood for microscopic examination, and color drawings of various cells in the human body. Added to inventory August 10, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 3 1083 Dupuytren, Guillaume. Matted lithograph of Guillaume Dupuytren (1777-1835). Ca. 1835. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 3 1084 Gillray, James. Engraving of James Gillray (1757-1815). From a miniature painted by himself. Engraved by Charles Turner, and published by G. Humphrey, London, April 19, 1819. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 3 1085 Willis, Thomas. Matted engraving of Thomas Willis (1621-1675). Impression by J & P Knapton, G. Vertus sculptor, London, 1742. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 3 1086 Crawford, T. Hamilton. Color print of T. Hamilton Crawford. Printed in 1934 by Frost and Reed Ltd., Bristol. England. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 3 1087 Urology. Lithograph illustrating a urological procedure. Lithograph by Englemann, ca 1820. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 3 1088 Eye Chart. Eye chart published by the American Medical Association, 1934. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 3 1089 Minnesota State Board of Health. Notice printed on cloth from the Minnesota State Board of Health, H.M. Bracken, Director, regarding laws on reporting births and deaths. Notice from ca. 1905 but possibly printed later. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 3 1090 Fox River (Illinois)Valley Medical Association. Published fee bill issued by the Fox River Valley Medical Association, October 3, 1864 enumerating standard fees for services. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 3 1091 New York State Department of Health. Bill of notice from Cressy L. Wilbur, M.D., Director, Division of Vital Statistics, New York State Department of Health urging the registration of new born babies. Notice published in English, Italian, Polish, Hungarian, Bohemian, and Yiddish. Published in Albany, New York, December 14, 1915. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 3 1092 Medical Research Council Ten Charts for the Calculation of Environmental Warmth. Supplement to War Memorandum No. 17. London: His Majesty’s Stationery Office, 1946. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 3 1093 Beaumont, William. Poster board containing William Beaumont’s family genealogical chart, 1640-1937. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 4 1094 Wolfe, Meyer. Photographic print of Vanderbilt Clinic by Meyer Wolfe, 1939. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 4 1095 Nashville, Tennessee. Color photocopy of Gray’s Map of the City of Nashville, ca. 1850. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 4 1096 Vanderbilt University. 300th General Hospital Unit. Map of southern Italy marked showing the location of the 300th General Hospital near Naples. Encapsulated in Mylar plastic sheeting. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 4 1097 Vanderbilt University Hospital. Poster board announcing the closing of the 5th and Elm Street Hospital on September 15, 1925 and the opening of the new Vanderbilt Hospital September 16, at 21st and Garland Avenue. Damaged. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 4 1098 Christie, Amos Uriah. Certificate from the Board of Medical Examiners of California certifying that Amos U. Christie is licenced to practice medicine in the state. Dated September 5, 1929. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 4 1099 Christie, Amos Uriah. Medical Degree awarded to Amos Christie from the University of California at Berkeley, May 15, 1929. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 4 1100 Christie, Amos Uriah. Framed photograph of Eureka High School football team, 1920. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 4 1101 Christie, Amos Uriah. Matted photograph of the 1923 University of Washington varsity football squad. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 4 1102 Christie, Amos Uriah. Wide-angle photograph mounted on board of the U.S. Naval Academy University of Washington Rose Bowl game, January 1, 1924. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 4 1103 Christie, Amos Uriah. Group photograph of Medical Department, R.O.T.C., Camp Lewis, Washington, June 15, 1926. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 4 1104 Christie, Amos Uriah. Group photograph of American Pediatric Society meeting, Skytop, Pennsylvania, April 27-29, 1939. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 5 1105 Colowick, Sidney P. Certificate from the American Cancer Society certifying that Sidney P. Colowick, Ph.D. was appointed the American Cancer Society -- Charles Hayden Foundation -- Research Professor of Microbiology at Vanderbilt, July 1, 1959. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 5 1106 Vanderbilt University. Navy V-12 Unit. Certificate of Merit from the Department of the Navy, Eighth Naval District to the V-12 Unit, Vanderbilt University for accomplishment in the sale and purchase of War Bonds, Pearl Harbor Day Campaign, 1944. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 5 1107 Meacham, Martin Alexander. Certificate of Licence for M.A. Meacham from the State Board of Medical Examiners of Tennessee, May 23, 1907. Poor condition, yellowing and crumbling. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 5 1108 Webb, Jack Benson. Non-Graduate Certificate of Permanent Licence for J. B. Webb from the State Board of Medical Examiners of Tennessee, November 6, 1907. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 5 1109 Bennett, Basil T. Certificate of license issued to Basil T. Bennett by the New Mexico Board of Health and Medical Examiners, April 8, 1909. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 5 1110 Bennett, Basil T. Certificate of permanent license issued to Basil T. Bennett by the State Board of Medical Examiners of Tennessee, May 3, 1909. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 5 1111 Throne, Binford. Diploma for B.A. degree from Vanderbilt University awarded to Binford Throne June 17, 1896. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 5 1112 Throne, Binford. Certificate of license issued to Binford Throne by the Board of Medical Examiners of the State of Tennessee, March 30, 1900. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 5 1113 Throne, Binford. Diploma from Randall’s Island and Infant’s Hospital, New York, certifying that Binford Throne was appointed one of the junior assistants to the house staff and subsequently served as a senior assistant and house physician and surgeon from June through December 1901. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 5 1114 Throne, Binford. License from the University of the State of New York to practice medicine and surgery in the state issued to Binford Throne June 2, 1904. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 5 1115 Throne, Binford. Certificate from the Department of health of the City of New York certifying that Binford Throne passed an examination and was appointed as an intern in the Contagious Disease Hospitals on December 5, 1906 and served 12 months. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 5 1116 Throne, Binford. Certificate from the American Board of Dermatology and Syphilogy certifying that Binford Throne is proficient in the practice of this specialty, June 11, 1934. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 5 1117 Briggs, Charles S. Letter from John M. Briggs of Bowling Green, Kentucky to Nathaniel Cross, Professor of Ancient Languages at the University of Nashville, inquiring about his son Charles S. Briggs, and about the possibility of establishing a medical school in Nashville. Dated March 3, 1842. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 6 1118 Morgan, Hugh Jackson. Diploma from Vanderbilt University for the Bachelor of Science degree awarded to Hugh Jackson Morgan, October 6, 1915. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 6 1119 Morgan, Hugh Jackson. Certificate from the U.S. government appointing Hugh Jackson Morgan First Lieutenant in the Medical Section of the Officer’s Reserve Corps of the Army of the United States. May 17, 1918. Added to inventory August 23, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 6 1120 Estes, Jack Milton. Diploma for the Doctor of Medicine degree from Vanderbilt University awarded to Jack Milton Estes, June 11, 1930. Added to inventory August 24, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 6 1121 Alsobrook, John Walter. Diploma for Doctor of Medicine degree from Vanderbilt University awarded to John Walter Alsobrook, April 5, 1904. Added to inventory August 24, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 6 1122 Hope, Franklin Levy. Diploma for Doctor of Medicine degree from Vanderbilt University awarded to Franklin Levi Hope, 1882. Parchment, written in Latin. Added to inventory August 24, 1995. Donated by Undine Levy, Memphis, Tennessee.
- Map Case Drawer 6 1123 Hope Franklin Levi. Certificate of membership from a fraternal organization (most likely Masonic) written in Latin. From Memphis and dated October 3, 1902. Added to inventory August 24, 1995. Donated by Undine Levy. Memphis, Tennessee.
- Map Case Drawer 6 1124 Frazer, Thomas Atchison. Diploma for Doctor of Medicine degree from Vanderbilt University awarded to Thomas Atchison Frazer, March 26, 1894. Parchment and written in Latin. Added to inventory August 24, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 6 1125 Roberts Richard R. Diploma for Doctor of Medicine degree from Vanderbilt University awarded to Richard R. Roberts, 1885. Parchment and written in Latin. Added to inventory August 24, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 6 1126 Oakley John Ferdinand. Diploma for Doctor of Medicine degree from Vanderbilt University awarded to John F. Oakley, 1890. Parchment and written in Latin. Added to inventory August 24, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 6 1127 Bennett, Basil Taylor. Diploma for Doctor of Medicine Degree from Vanderbilt University awarded to Basil T. Bennett, 1893. Parchment and written in Latin. Added to inventory August 24, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 7 1128 Transylvania University. Diploma for Doctor of Medicine degree from Transylvania University awarded to John Robertson Wilson, 1825. Parchment and written in Latin. Added to inventory August 24, 1995.
- Map Case Drawer 7 1129 Lewis, Robert. Diploma for Doctor of Medicine degree from the University of Nashville awarded to Robert Lewis March 1, 1862, Parchment, written in Latin, and damaged at bottom. Added to inventory August 24, 1995.